<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Jackrabbit operations explained</title>
 </properties>
 <body>
<section name="How Jackrabbit works">
<p>
The diagram on the left explains which components of the Jackrabbit
are used when a user of the JCR API modified content in the content
repository. This is a simple and very common operation, that touches 
a large portion of the components in the Jackrabbit implementation.
Please keep in mind that this implementation architecture is not
mandated by JCR, but has been designed from scratch based on JCR.
</p>
<p>
<img src="../../../images/arch/jackrabbit-ism_small.jpg" /><br/>
The used components and their respective functions in the order
of their appearance in the use case of writing or modifying 
content in the content repository:
<ul>
<li><b>Transient Item State Manager</b>
Once content items are read by a session they are cached in
the Transient Item State Manager. When those items are modified
the modification is only visible to that same session, in the 
so-called "transient" space.</li>

<li><b>Transactional Item State Manager</b>
When the Application persists the modified items using the 
JCR <code>Item.save()</code> or <code>Session.save()</code> the
transient Items are promoted into the Transactional ISM.
The modifications are still only visible within the scope
of this transaction, meaning that other sessions will not
see the modification until they are committed. The commit
is implicit if the Content Repository is not running in an XA environment.
</li>

<li><b>Shared Item State Manager</b>
Once a transaction is committed the Shared Item State Manager
receives the changelog and publishes the changes to all the sessions 
logged into the same workspace. This means that all the Item States
that are cached and referenced by other sessions are notified 
and possibly updated or invalidated.
The Shared Item State Manager also triggers the observation and
hands the changelog over to the persistence manager that is 
configured for this workspace.</li>

<li><b>Persistence Manager</b>
The Persistence Manager persists all the Item States in the 
changelog passed by the Shared ISM. The persistence manager
is a very simple, fast and transactional interface that is
very low-level and does not need to understand the complexities
of the repository operations, but basically just needs to be 
able persist and retrieve a given item based on its item id.
</li>

<li><b>Observation</b>
When a transaction is committed the Shared Item State Manager
triggers the Observation mechanism. This allows applications
to asynchronously subscribe changes in the workspace. 
Jackrabbit also non-standard offers a synchronous observation.
</li>

<li><b>Query Manager / Index</b>
Through a synchronous observation event the Query Manager is
instructed to index the new or modified items. A content 
repository index is much more complex than a classical RDB
index since it deals with content repository features like 
the item hierarchy, nodetype inheritance or fulltext 
searches.</li>

</ul>
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
