<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>QueryManager implementation details</title>
 </properties>
 <body>
<section name="Overview">
<p>
Jackrabbit implements both the mandatory XPath and optional SQL 
query syntax. Its design follows the goal of the JSR-170 specification
that all the mandatory query features can be expressed either in
XPath or in SQL. Thus, the actual implementation of the query engine
is independent of the query syntax used, though Jackrabbit's query
internals are closer to XPath than SQL, because of the hierarchical
structure of a JCR.
</p>
<p>
The major parts of the query implementation are:
<ul>
<li>XPath Parser</li>
<li>SQL Parser</li>
<li>Abstract Query Tree</li>
<li>Query engine</li>
<li>Utilities</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>

<section name="XPath Parser">
<p>
The XPath query parser is based on the W3C XQuery grammar definition which
is not yet final but can be downloaded as draft
<a href="http://www.w3.org/2005/02/applets/xgrammar.zip">here</a>.
The reason why Jackrabbit uses the XQuery grammar, rather than the XPath
grammar, is, that JSR-170 specifies an 'order by' clause for the XPath
query syntax. This 'order by' clause is borrowed from the
<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/#id-flwor-expressions">XQuery FLWOR</a>
expression syntax. Before parsing the XPath query in Jackrabbit, the statement
is surrounded with dummy code, to form a valid XQuery FLWOR expression and
is then passed to the XQuery parser.
</p>
<p>
The actual parser is a class generated by JavaCC, which uses the grammar
that can be found in <code>src/grammar/xpath</code>.
</p>
<p>
The parsed XPath statement is then translated into an Abstract Query Tree.
See class:
<code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.xpath.XPathQueryBuilder</code>
</p>
</section>

<section name="SQL Parser">
<p>
The SQL query parser is generated from a grammar definition located in
<code>src/grammar/sql</code>. After parsing, the Abstract Syntax Tree
is translated into the Jackrabbit internal Abstract Query Tree.
See class:
<code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.sql.JCRSQLQueryBuilder</code>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Abstract Query Tree">
<p>
The Abstract Query Tree (AQT) is the common query description format that
allows Jackrabbit to implement a query engine which is (to a certain
extent) independent of the query syntax used (XPath or SQL).
The AQT consists of the classes that are derived from:
<code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.QueryNode</code>
</p>
<p>
Please note that the AQT is Jackrabbit internal and not exposed to a client
using the JCR API!
</p>
</section>

<section name="Query Engine">
<p>
Now this is where the meat is. The actual implementation of the query engine
is configurable. One needs to implement the interface:
<code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.QueryHandler</code>. Jackrabbit comes
with an implementation that uses a <a href="http://lucene.apache.org/">Lucene</a>
index: <code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.lucene.SearchIndex</code> This
index is independent of the persistence manager in use. However
it is also possible to write a <code>QueryHandler</code> implementation which is
aware of the underlying storage (e.g. a database) and executes the query on
the 'native' storage.
</p>
<p>
The class <code>org.apache.core.query.lucene.LuceneQueryBuilder</code> translates
the Abstract Query Tree into a query that can be executed against the Lucene
index. Jackrabbit implements a couple of extensions to the standard Lucene
classes, primarily to improve performance in an environment with incremental
indexing like Jackrabbit. Instead of a single index, Jackrabbit uses generations
of indexes to circumvent costly IndexReader / IndexWriter creation. See:
<code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.lucene.MultiIndex</code>. The most
recent generation of the search index is held completely in memory. See:
<code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.lucene.VolatileIndex</code>. It is
comparable with the garbage collection in Java, where generations are used to
move living objects from the young into the old generation over time. Queries
are then executed on a MultiReader that spans all the indexes. Every now and
then (depending on the configuration parameters in workspace.xml) indexes
are merged and nodes marked as deleted in the index are removed. This happens
similar to how Lucene merges its internal segments.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Utilities">
<p>
The class <code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.QueryParser</code> allows you
to translate a query statement into an Abstract Query Tree and vice versa. It's
a nice tool to see how a query in XPath looks like in SQL or the other way round.
</p>
<p>
The class <code>org.apache.jackrabbit.core.query.PropertyTypeRegistry</code>
provides fast access to the type information based on property names. The
Jackrabbit QueryHandler implementation uses this class to coerce value literals
into other value types.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
