<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Copyright 2004-2005 The Apache Software Foundation or its licensors,
                       as applicable.

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Overview</title>
 </properties>
 <body>

<section name="Apache Jackrabbit">
<p>
The Jackrabbit Project has been formed to develop an open source implementation
of the Content Repository for Java Technology API (JCR), being specified within
the Java Community Process as
<a href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=170">JSR-170</a>.
<a href="http://www.day.com/">Day Software</a>, the JSR-170 specification lead,
has licensed an initial implementation of the JCR reference implementation for
use as seed code for this project.  JCR specifies an API for application
developers (and application frameworks) to use for interaction with modern
content repositories that provide content services such as searching, versioning, 
transactions, etc.
</p>
<p>
Jackrabbit's implementation began as a proposal within the
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/index.html">Jakarta Slide</a>project,
but has since attracted interest from multiple projects with the
<a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>, including
Slide, Cocoon, Lenya, XML Indexing, Axion, and Derby.  We are also looking at
integration with projects such as Beehive, Maven, and Portals.
</p>
<p>
The purpose of this incubation period is to attract additional contributors
from other Apache projects and from the various JSR-170 expert group companies,
learn the Apache way of doing things, and allow the developers to focus on this
interface/implementation rather than all of the existing projects that might
want to use it.  We hope to improve collaboration on the code base by moving
all of the active developers and authors to Apache, bring in as many of the
Apache veterans as wish to get involved, and open it up to all of the 22 expert
group companies.  Development of the JCR RI and TCK will occur in this project
-- Day Software plans to continue participation in Jackrabbit and use the code
in the official (binary) RI and TCK releases, allowing developers to beta test
against the open source versions as well as the official versions.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Releases">
<p>
See the <a href="downloads.html">downloads</a> page for information on
obtaining releases.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Documentation">
<p>
The <a href="apidocs/index.html">JavaDoc API documents</a> are available online.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
