<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Building Jackrabbit</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Building Jackrabbit">
      <p>
        The easiest way to use Jackrabbit is to
        <a href="../downloads.cgi">download</a> a binary release, but if you
        want to access the latest development version, you need to get the
        Jackrabbit sources and build them using the
        <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven 2</a> build environment.
      </p>
      <p>
        The first step in building Jackrabbit is to check out the Jackrabbit
        sources from the <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>
        source repository at
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/">http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/</a>.
        The source tree is divided in standard parts:
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/trunk/">trunk</a>,
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/branches/">branches</a>, and
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/tags/">tags</a>.
        The latest development version is found within trunk, while the
        other parts are used to keep track of the source code of the
        Jackrabbit releases.
      </p>
      <p>
        The trunk contains the top-level build environment and a number of
        component projects within subdirectories. See the
        <code>README.txt</code> files within each subdirectory for a brief
        description of the component project. There is also a
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/trunk/contrib/">contrib</a>
        directory with miscellaneous contributions that are not yet a part
        of the official Jackrabbit releases.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Checking out the sources with Subversion">
        <p>
          You need a <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>
          client to access the Jackrabbit source repository. Take a look at the
          <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/project_links.html#clients">Subversion client list</a>
          unless you already have a one installed. Once you have the Subversion
          client installed you can checkout the main Jackrabbit source tree
          with the following command or its equivalent in the client you are using:
        </p>
        <source>svn checkout http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/jackrabbit/trunk jackrabbit</source>
        <p>
          The above checkout will create a subdirectory named
          <code>jackrabbit</code> that contains the latest Jackrabbit sources.
          See the <a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">Subversion book</a>
          or the documentation of your Subversion client for more information
          on how to manage your source tree and keep it up to date with latest
          development.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Building the sources with Maven">
        <p>
          Jackrabbit uses <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven 2</a>
          as the build system and the component sources are mostly organized
          according to the Maven
          <a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/introduction/introduction-to-the-standard-directory-layout.html"
            >Standard Directory Layout</a>. The standard build environment
          is Maven 2 with the Java Development Kit (JDK) 1.4, but the build
          is known to work also with Java 5 and 6.
        </p>
        <p>
          See the
          <a href="http://maven.apache.org/run-maven/index.html">Running Maven</a>
          page and the related documentation on the Maven web site for
          instructions on how to use Maven. You may also want to check for
          Maven 2 integration with your favourite Integrated Development
          Environment (IDE).
        </p>
        <p>
          There are Maven project descriptors (POMs) within both the top
          level <code>jackrabbit</code> directory you checked out above
          and all the <code>jackrabbit-<em>something</em></code> component
          subdirectories. The easiest way to build Jackrabbit is to use
          the "multimodule" setup within the top level directory:
        </p>
        <source>$ cd /path/to/jackrabbit; mvn install</source>
        <p>
          This will build and package all the component projects and place
          the resulting artifacts within your local Maven 2 repository. You
          can also find the artifacts within the created <code>target</code>
          subdirectories of the component projects.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
